When I started working at Google, I was
коли я почав працювати в в Гуглі мене
really impressed by how quickly you can
дуже вразило Наскільки швидко можна
launch a project you're working on. All you
підняти проект над яким ти працюєш Все
need is to open a browser,
що треба - це просто відкрити браузер
open a specific URL, and that's it. The
відкрити певний URL і все в тебе
code editor in the browser is all in the browser,
редактор коду в браузері все в браузері
and on your laptop, all you need is a
і на твоєму лептопі все що треба щоб
browser. And I thought, is it possible to
було тільки браузер і я подумав чи можна
set up the same thing outside of Google? And
таке саме налаштувати за межами Гугла і
in fact, that's what we're going to do today? Yes,
насправді ми сьогодні цим і займемось Да
today we're going to try to start
давайте ми сьогодні спробуємо запустити
development purely in the browser, so that there's nothing
розробку чисто в браузері щоб нічого
superfluous, so that we can work with the code,
зайвого щоб ми могли працювати з кодом
so that we can open our application that we're
щоб ми могли відкрити наш додаток які ми
developing, so that we can install
розробляємо щоб ми могли поставити
plugins, and so that all these settings
плегіни і щоб це все всі ці налаштування
are stored somewhere on the server, and all we
десь зберігались на сервері і все що нам
need is a browser. And as
треба було локальне - це браузер і як
always, we'll divide the video into several
завжди ми розділимо відео на декілька
parts. First, we'll talk about
частин Спочатку ми поговоримо про
the architecture of VCD, then we'll talk about
архітектуру vcд потім ми поговоримо про
development through SSG and see how it
розробку через ssж і подивимося як воно
all works, and then, through development
все працює і потім вже через розробку
through the browser, well, in essence, it's all
через браузер е ну по суті це все буде
about VSCode. It should be interesting. Let's
про vскод має бути цікаве давайте
draw a little story about VSCode. VSCode
малювати трішечки історії про vscд vsкод
originally started as  web editor in
спочатку починався як веб-редактор в
the browser and this editor was called
браузері і називався цей редак редактор
monako editor and even now we
monнако і навіть зараз ми його
use it on some projects That is,
використовуємо на деяких проектах Тобто
you can install this editor yourself
ви можете проінсталити цей редактор собі
add to your program a full-fledged
додати в вашу програму повноцінний
editor similar to vsko for editing
редактор схожий на vsко для редагування
files with all the features. Once upon a time in 2011 there was
файлів з усіма фішками колись в 2011 був
monak and it was written on the basis of
monak і він був написаний на базі
technology. At some point it was transferred
технології в якійсь момент його перевели
to Electron. Electron is a kind of
на Електрон то електрон - це така собі
shell that allows you to run our
оболонка яка дозволяє запускати нашу
webapp and simultaneously use
вебабку і одночасно використовувати і
node.jspi and the browser API, but our UI
node.jspi і браузерній API але наш ui
is written in HTML and CSS, in essence, vscd
написано на HTML і CSS по суті vscд
looked like this then. It was just
виглядав тоді отак от Це просто було
its core and this shell on electron and at
його і ця оболонка на електроні і і на
that time there were no plugins and
той момент не було якихось плагінів і
the question arose that it was necessary to add
виникло питання що необхідно додавати
plugins and then It was decided that plugins
плагіни і тоді Було вирішено що плагіни
should be in a separate process, that is,
мають бути в окремому процесі тобто
extensions - this is a separate process and some kind of
розширення - це окремий процес і якась
communication with the kernel. This allowed it to
комунікація з ядром це дозволило швидко
start quickly, not overload the kernel,
стартувати не перевантажувати ядро
have more stability, and so on. And
більше мати стабільність і так далі І
also the goal of vcode was to support
також ціль у vкода була підтримувати
the maximum number of languages, and accordingly it
максимальну кількість мов і відповідно
was necessary to write  or a plugin that somehow
треба було писати або плагін який якось
cooperates with the editor or another
співпрацює з редактором або виникла інша
idea arose to make so-called language servers. This is
ідея зробити так звані langдж сервера Це
another separate process, for example, there for
ще один окремий процес наприклад там для
java or for node.js or something else that is
jaви чи для node.js чи ще для чогось які
launched separately and via rpc that
запускаються окремо і по rpc який
communicates with our process in which
спілкується з нашим процесом в якому є
our eyes already have extensions. I looked at
вже наші оці от розширення Я дивився
the hearts, it seems that this is json rpc, that is,
серци здається що це json rpc тобто в
we already have the core of our vs-code, the main
нас уже є ядро нашого vs-кода основний
process, then there is a process in which
процес потім є процес в якому
extensions are launched and there is a process that
запускаються екстеншени і є процес який
is essentially a language server and we have a
по суті є language сервером і у нас є
certain language Server puncture for
певний language Server прокол для
communication and it has been there for some time. In
комунікації і це вже був якийсь час там
2015, the Windows subsystem for Linux appeared
2015 з'явився Windows subsstem for Linux
and there was a need to run vs-code
і виникла необхідність запускати vs-код
in one place in Windows, and the program code itself
в одному місці в Віндовсі а а сам код
that we write should be launched already in
програми якою ми пишемо запускати вже в
Linux and it is necessary and accordingly we have a
лінуксі і необхідно і відповідно у нас
different file system there, other paths, we
там інша файлова система інші шляхи ми
launch other processes for debugging and we had to
запускаємо інші процеси для дебагінгу і
somehow separate it and then the
треба було якось це розділяти і тоді
following idea appeared: If we
з'явилась ідея наступна Якщо у нас і так
already have extensions - this is a separate process. Let's
вже еншни - це окремий процес Давайте
Let's do this, let's launch the vsl agent and here
зробимо так запустимо агента vsl і тут у
we can have our own extensions
нас можуть бути в нього свої ексттеншени
in this process and our core will be the core
в цьому процесі і наш кор буде ядро
vscode will communicate with the agent or
vsкод буде спілкуватися з м агентом або
with the local process or here or
з локальним процесом або тут або
respectively vsl S exens and also
відповідно vsl S exensними і так само
here we can launch some
тут ми можемо запустити який-небудь
language Server there Java or something else that
language Server там Java чи ще щось який
communicates via the language Server
спілкується через language Server
protocol and accordingly if you
протокол і відповідно якщо на це
look at it then in principle it's not much
подивитися то в принципі не сильно
It's far from development via ssh because
Далеко це від розробки через ssh тому що
instead of a regular agent we can
замість а звичайного агента у нас може
have an agent that works via ss to
бути агент який працює через ss для
work via the browser here it's a little more complicated
роботи через браузер тут трохи складніше
because our core should not rely on the
тому що наше ядро має не спиратися на
node.js API and use only
node.js API і використовувати тільки
browser APIs and it's a little more complicated That's why
браузерні API і це дещо складніше Тому
it was added only in the 20th year and now
це було Додано лише в 20-му році і тепер
Let's try to configure it now we are
Давайте спробуємо налаштувати нас зараз
interested in configuring access via ss
цікавить налаштування доступу через ssж
What I have already done I launched some server
що я вже зробив я запустив деякий сервер
on the Internet in Google Cloud with a small
в інтернеті в Google Клауді з невеличким
program
програму
My webup you see and made a small
My webup ви бачите і зробив невеличкий
htp server that simply accepts the request and issues
htp сервер який просто приймає запит
back Hello world or Hello name and
видає назад Hello world або Hello name і
name is the parameter that came in the URL
name - це параметр який прийшов в URL
let's see this is our  directory
давайте подивимось оце наша директорія в
basically there is nothing here except
принципі тут нічого нічого нема крім
our myweb App I will also show you an
нашого myweb App Також я вам покажу
interesting thing I will show that no processes are
цікаву штуку я покажу що ніяких процесів
running on the server this is an important
з на сервері не запущено це важливий
point Now let's configure our
момент Тепер давайте налаштуємо наш
vss code the first thing that needs to be
всs-код перше що має бути мають бути
installed plugins for remote
встановлені плагіни для віддаленої
development in principle you will find them Remote
розробки в принципі їх знайдете Remote
Development Remote ss vscode and this is a plugin
Development Remote ss vscode і це плагін
from Microsoft and now we can
від майкрософту і тепер ми можемо
connect to our host and a
під'єднатися до нашого хаста і в мене
new window has opened that is already connected
відкрилось нове вікно яке вже підключене
we see ssh dev Host and you may
ми бачимо ssh dev Host і ви можете
think that we just connected via
подумати що ми просто підключились по
ssh and look at the files that are on
ssh і дивимось файли які знаходяться у
my server here somewhere on
мене От на цьому от мо сервері десь в
the Internet actually not if I now
інтернеті насправді ні якщо я зараз
execute the same command to look at the
виконаю ту саму команду щоб подивитись
running processes you will see that I
запущені процеси ви побачите що в мене
already have additional processes running on the server
вже на сервері запущені додаткові
some vscde Sever and you see
процеси якийсь vscde Север і ви бачите
that if I look at Directories then I have a
що якщо я подивлюсь Директорії то в мене
vscod Sever directory i.e.
з'явилась директорія vscod Север тобто
vscd when you connect posssh some
vscд коли ви підключаєте поssш якусь
directory from a remote server then it
директорію з віддаленого сервера то Він
installs its server there and starts
встановлює туди свій сервер і запускає
it  and now let's try to open
його а тепер Давайте спробуємо відкрити
the directory here it asks for the path I take
директорію ось воно питає шлях Я беру от
our mywebup directory open and we
нашу директорію mywebup відкриваю і ми
see this file that we have
бачимо оцей файлік що у нас розташований
on the server In addition, we can have a
на сервері Крім того ми можемо мати тут
full terminal here and even more we
повноцінний термінал і навіть більше ми
can run our server now it will
можемо запустити зараз наш сервер воно
wake up the desktop That is you can open in
прокине парти Тобто можна відкрити в
the browser and the application that is running on the
браузері і додаток який запущений на
server will open locally or
сервері відкриється у нас локально або
Preview ineditor you can see it completely It works
Preview ineditor бачите повністю Вона
works I go to
відпрацьовує працює я заходжу на
127001 port 3000 and this port is automatically
127001 порт 3000 і цей порт автоматично
redirected to the server to the port that
перенаправляється на сервер на порт який
my application is listening to here we see
слухає моя аплікуха от ми бачимо
forwarded adress
forwardwarded adress
1270013000 is redirected to port
1270013000 перенаправляється на порт
3000 on this remote server and it
3000 на цьому віддалому сервері і воно
says autoforwarded so we can
каже autofwardwarded от і ми можемо
add some other port 300010
додати якийсь інший порт 300010
for example and this port is not currently
наприклад і цей порт зараз ніяка
listening to any application we don't see any
аплікуха не слухає ми не бачимо ніяких
running processes but if we have
запущених процесів але якщо у нас буде
this process running Accordingly we will
запущений цей процес Відповідно ми
be able to connect and see how it
зможемо під'єднатися і побачити як воно
all works let's go further now I
все працює давайте тепер підемо далі я
format something for myself save and  I want
собі щось форматую зберігаю і я хочу щоб
it to be beautifully
воно в мене красиво автоматично
formatted automatically and for this I need to
форматувалось і для цього Мені треба
install the prer plugin I go to
встановити плагін prer я заходжу в
extensions and you see that now we have
extensions і ви бачите що у нас тепер
extensions written local 36 pieces
extensions написано локальні 36 штук
installed And the extensions that
проінстальовано І екстншени які
are installed on the remote server and there are
встановлені на віддаленому сервері і їх
zero of them so far Let me enter prp found
поки що нуль Давайте я введу prр знайшов
And now I have a button to put on the
І тепер у мене є кнопочка поставити на
remote server that is this preter plin
віддалений сервер тобто цей preter plin
will not be launched locally but will be
буде запущений не в мене локально а буде
launched on the remote server and will
запущений на віддаленому сервері і буде
work with the same code that is remote
працювати з тим тим кодом що віддалений
Let me now try to press save
Давайте я тепер спробую нажати зберегти
op and everything is formatted for me that is the
оп і в мене все відформатувалося тобто
plugin works great come on so let's
плагін класно працює давай так давайте
now try to run the debugger We
тепер спробуємо запустити дебагер У нас
have a Run debug tab before
є вкладка Run debug перед тим як
running it let's stop our
запускати його давайте зупинимо наш
process that we launched in the terminal because
процес який ми запустили в терміналі бо
we will already have a busy port let's run
в нас буде вже зайнятий порт запускаємо
and everything started Preview everything
і у нас все запустилось Preview все
works Let's try to pass some
працює Давайте спробуємо передати якийсь
parameter name is equal to javascript works
параметр name дорівнює javascript працює
and Now let's put some
і Тепер давайте поставимо який-небудь
here breakpint again javascript 2
тут breakpint ще раз javascript 2
send a request and see what we have  The
відправляємо запит і дивимось що у нас е
debugger is working, the variable name already has
наш deбагер працює змінна name має вже
javascript 2 values, let's continue, that is, everything
javascript 2 value продовжиємо тобто все
works without any problems and we work.
працює без всяких проблем і ми працюємо
Through ss, it's as if we were working
Через ss Ніби ми ніби б ми працювали
locally and also remotely, our
локально і також віддалено нас може
language server can work, our plugins and In
працювати language serве наші плагіни і
addition, we can manage all these plugins and
Крім того ми можемо всі ці плагіни
extensions normally through
екстеншни нормально менеджерити через
vscode and see which ones are running locally, which
vsкод і бачити які запущені локальна які
we see. It's already on the dev host now.
от ми бачимо Є вже на dev Host тепер
Let's try to do without the
Давайте спробуємо взагалі обійтись без
installed vscode at all and do all this
встановленого vs-код і все це зробити
through the browser. To run vscode in the
через браузер щоб запустити vscд в
browser, you just need to go to vscod.dv,
браузері просто треба зайти на vscod.dv
this is a site from Microsoft. You just
цей сайт від Microsoft ви просто
go to vscod.dv and use
Заходите в vscod.dv і користуєтесь
vscode. You can open the directory,
вескодом ви можете відкрити директорію
but you won't be able to run the language
але ви не зможете тут запустити language
server here. You won't be able to run the ense if you
Server не зможете запустити еensшни якщо
just open some local
просто відкриєте який небудь локальний
file or local directory because you
файл чи локальну директорію тому що десь
need to run all these processes somewhere, but we
треба запускати всі ці процеси але в нас
have here, not just open the Open
є тут не просто відкрити директорію Open
Folder directory, but join, connect to the
Folder але є доєднатися підключитися до
tunnel, but first we see that it
тунелю але спочатку ми бачимо воно
asks to go to github, I'll explain later
просить зайти в github я поясню пізніше
why this is needed. We've already gone to
для чого це потрібно все ми вже зайшли в
github, now we have our  vscod.df
github тепер у нас наш vscod.df
is authorized with tkhaubm and that's good Now
авторизований з тхаubм і це добре Тепер
we need to put a tunnel on our
нам треба поставити тунель на нашу
remote machine and here there are two options
віддалену машину і тут є два варіанти
but the easiest is probably to download vscode
але найпростіше мабуть от скачати vscode
CLI
CLI
unpack it and we have one binary
розпакувати його і у нас є один бінар
which we just have to run with the word
який ми маємо просто запустити зі словом
Tunnel and in principle this should be
Tunnel і в принципі цього має бути
enough look further what it offers
достатньо дивіться далі що він пропонує
it says to give access to this server
він каже щоб дати доступ у цьому серверу
please go to this github
будь ласка зайдіть на цей от github
devvaice go it asks to enter the
devваice заходим воно просить ввести
activation code copy enter the
активаційний код копіюємо вводимо
activation code click continue it
активаційний код нажимаємо continue воно
says that some server is requesting
каже що якийсь сервер запрошує
authorization yes this is my server in
авторизацію да це сервер в мене в
Germany Let's try to press Ora
Німеччині Давайте спробуємо нажати Ора
all access is what we now have in the terminal
все доступ є що у нас тепер в терміналі
asks what to name this machine Let it be
питає як назвати цю машину Хай
called dev Host and we create a
називається dev Host і у нас створюється
tunnel now we just copy this URL
тунель тепер ми просто копіюємо цей URL
we see that this URL is no longer not not on
ми бачимо що цей URL вже не не не на
github but on vscde Def It's just
github а На vscde Def Це просто
automatic for us Uh Sorry I
автоматично нам Ух Вибачте я його
stopped it let's run it again a second time
зупинив давайте ще раз запущу другий раз
we don't have to do anything like that we
ми вже нічого не маємо такого робити ми
just run everything all the settings
просто запускаємо все всі налаштування
are saved and look we copied this
збережені і дивіться ми скопіювали цей
URL  we try and now we click
URL пробуємо і тепер ми нажимаємо
open directory we see Directories from
відкрити директорію бачимо Директорії з
our server our myweb App we click
нашого сервера наш myweb App нажимаємо
ok Everything works we say trust we have
окей Все працює кажемо довіряємо маємо
Here is our server Let's try to
Тут наш сервер Давайте спробуємо
look at our extensions
подивитися на наші екстеншени
it works That is our exnsh which we then
це працює Тобто наш exнш який ми тоді
installed via ssh it is also
встановили через ssh він так само
available when working simply through the
доступний при роботі просто через
browser let's now try to
браузер давайте тепер спробуємо
run terminals try to run
запустити термінали спробуємо запустити
debugger we have debugger click Run B
debager в нас є debager нажимаємо Run B
node.js starts deber I suggest
node.js запускається deber пропоную
to open in the browser well we open
відкрити в браузері добре відкриваємо
but we see that the URL is no longer Local Host
але ми бачимо що URL вже не Local Host
already some kind of special URL dev
вже якийсь такий спеціальний URL dev
tunnels and accordingly our
tunnels і відповідно запустилась наша
program Hello world started try to add
програма Hello world спробуємо додати
name
name
javascript click everything works let's
javascript нажимаємо все працює давайте
add
додамо
breakpint write javascript 2 press
breakpint пишу javascript 2 нажимаю
Enter and see stopped Here is
Enter і бачимо зупинились Ось на нашому
our variable name ports
брейкпоінті є наша змінна name порти
are woken up extensions that is we now have
прокинуті ексттеншени тобто у нас тепер
full work through the browser everything that
повноцінна работа через браузер все що в
we had through sssh and with the local machine
нас було через ssш і з локальною машиной
everything now works through the browser We have
все тепер працює через браузер У нас є
debugger We have full local
дебагр У нас є повноцінна локальна
development We have  extensions, that is, I can
розробка У нас є екстншени тобто я можу
now go to any other machine, all
тепер зайти на будь-яку іншу машину все
I need to do is open this URL
що мені треба буде це відкрити цей URL
vscod.df/tunnel/ the name of my machine, but
vscod.df/tunnel/ назва моєї машини але
I need to be authorized on the hub
мені треба бути авторизованим на тхабі
so that GitHub can wake up the tunnel
для того щоб giththub прокинув тунель
because I am not indirectly connecting to
тому що я не непряму підключаюсь до
my machine, but I am connecting to GitHub
своєї машини а я підключаюсь до гитхаubу
from a browser. I think it works through
з браузера Я думаю це працює через
web sockets and similarly my machine, my
вебсокети і так само моя машина мій
server where I am from where my code is located,
сервер де я з де в мене розташований код
also connects to some kind of conditional
також під'єднується до до якогось умовно
proxy and it connects us and we and I can
проксі і він з'єднує нас і ми і я можу
sit behind NAT, there is no problem and I think
сидіти за натом проблеми немає і я думаю
that that server can also sit behind NAT and
що той сервер теж може сидіти за натом і
behind a firewall and everything will work and the same thing
за фаерволом і все буде працювати і і те
happens when you start the folder. That is, we
саме відбувається запуска мапки Тобто ми
started it and we see that we have
її запустили і ми бачимо що у нас є
some special domain that
якийсь спеціальний домен який
connects to some kind of proxy and some kind of
конектиться на якусь праксю і якась
proxy already through that tunnel connects
прокся вже через той тунель з'єднується
to the vscod server which is located on
з vscд сервером який розташований на
our server where our code is located and
нашому сервері де розташований наш код і
if you enter the word Development in Google,
якщо ви в Google введете взково мо
you will be given a page  In
Development вам видасть сторінка
the documentation you see a similar diagram as I
документації ви бачите схожа схема як Я
drew and we have several options,
малював і у нас є декілька варіантів
let's remember through ss for
згадаємо через ss для
vsl there is github code Spaces there is through the browser
vsl є github code Spaces є через браузер
in fact code Spaces works completely I understand it
по суті code Spaces працює Я так розумію
completely Similarly and there is also development in
повністю Аналогічно і також є розробка в
containers development in containers - this is
контейнерах розробка в контейнерах - це
generally a cool thing you will develop
взагалі крута штука ви будете розробляти
everything locally but your application will
все локально але ваша аплікуха повністю
run completely in the container all extensions
запуститься в контейнері всі ектеншени
will be installed in the container and this is also a
встановлються в контейнері і це ж теж
Zero Click setup just local
такий Zero Click setup просто локальна
I hope it was interesting and useful like the
сподіваюсь що було цікаво і корисно
video write comments
ставте лайк відео пишіть коментарі
Subscribe separately Thank you very much to
Підписуйтесь окрема Дякую величезно
the sponsors for the support it is very motivating
спонсорам за підтримку це дуже мотивує
to record new and new videos and if you
записувати нові і нові відео і якщо ви
suddenly decided to support the channel and also
раптом вирішили підтримати канал і теж
become a sponsor please here is a
стати спонсором будь ласка ось є
link to the video where I
посилання на відео де я
talked about different levels of sponsorship
розповідав про різні рівні спонсорства